<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Optimization on The ML Surgeon</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/optimization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Optimization on The ML Surgeon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© 2024 Dario Salvati</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/optimization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Performing Kernel Surgery: Profiling CUDA Kernels with NVIDIA Nsight Compute</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/profiling-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/profiling-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Being a Machine Learning Surgeon is not an easy life. We not only have to deal with intricate machine learning systems but also navigate the additional complexities surrounding them. To be a proficient ML Surgeon, we must develop a diverse skill set.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Machine Learning Surgeon’s Toolkit: Advanced Matrix Multiplication in CUDA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/matrix-multiplication/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/matrix-multiplication/</guid>
      <description>During the first year of my Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Computer Science, I had to complete a project for a Machine Learning course. It involved implementing a small feed-forward neural network framework from scratch, using only numerical libraries and coding elements such as loss functions, backpropagation, and the feed-forward step.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Sparsity for Efficient Neural Network Inference</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pruning-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pruning-intro/</guid>
      <description>NOTE: This post was written before the Machine Learning Surgeon got in charge of the blog, that&amp;rsquo;s why there are no references to surgical operations!
Large Language Model. How many times did you read that term?</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
